{"tossups": [{"question": "Victor Ostrovsky has written several books about his time with this organization, which undertook Operation Plumbat to obtain 200 tons of yellowcake from a German freighter. This organization attacked a group operating out of Factory 333 as part of Operation Damocles. Members of this organization accidentally killed an innocent waiter in Lillehammer, Norway during one operation. While working for this organization, Cheryl Hanin lured whistle-blower Mordechai Vanunu into custody. Members of this organization are known as katsas. This organization, which works alongside Aman and Shin Bet, was responsible for killing several members of the Black September organization in the wake of the Munich Olympics, and was also responsible for capturing Adolf Eichmann in Argentina. For 10 points, identify this organization, Israel's intelligence agency.", "answer": "Mossad [or HaMossad leModi'in uleTafkidim Meyuchadim, accept Israeli Intelligence before mention]", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This process is stopped by the 911 complex, and it is prevented from repeating itself via binding of geminin. CAF1 and ASF1 are chaperone proteins key to coordinating nucleosome deposition during this process. One key enzyme in this process is assisted by a trimer of PCNA proteins, which forms a sliding clamp. Sites in which this process will initiate bind to a hexamer of MCM proteins, and are known as origins. Flap endonucleases remove the primers used in this process, whose strict directionality requires the formation of Okazaki fragments on the lagging strand. This process is initiated by the action of helicase, which forms a bubble in which polymerase synthesizes a new strand from 5-prime to 3-prime. For 10 points, name this semiconservative process in which a cell's genome is copied.", "answer": "DNA replication [prompt on S phase, prompt on the cell cycle]", "subcategory": "Science Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This event was facilitated by the defense-in-depth strategy implemented by General Fagalde. Before this event, Marshal Gort rejected a joint-counterattack plan towards Bapaume by General Weygand as suicidal. An order by the attacking side to halt for three days while 25 kilometres from the site of this event also provided time for preparation. During the middle of this event, the Belgian Army surrendered, leaving a 30 km hole in the defenses. Explanations for that decision included Goering persuading Hitler that the Luftwaffe would be enough to destroy the defenders of this event. This event saw the participation of nearly 900 boats, military and civilian. For 10 points, name this Second World War event that saw 330 000 French and British troops evacuated from the German advance a certain French Channel port city.", "answer": "Dunkirk Evacuation or Miracle of Dunkirk or Operation Dynamo [accept anything related to Allied troops taken out of Dunkirk by ships; prompt on \"Dunkirk\" or \"Battle of Dunkirk\"]", "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In one play by this author, the Marshal in charge of the unnamed setting doesn't care that people over the age of forty-five are dying to the title ailment, because the youthful members of the military are unaffected. In another play, this author wrote of a technological advance that allowed humans to annihilate matter to generate energy, but the byproduct causes world wide strife. This author of The White Disease and The Absolute at Large created the Captain von Toch who discovers the title creatures of another work near Sumatra before those creatures exploited by humans. In his most famous work, this author created Harry Domain, the manager of the title company that produces automata. For 10 points, name this Czech author of War with the Newts and R.U.R.", "answer": "Karel Capek", "subcategory": "Literature European", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "One of this composer's friends mistook the term \"parts\" to mean number of movements when he actually meant number of musical lines, leading to his three-hour work Music in Twelve Parts, composed several years after his Music in Similar Motion. This man's fourth symphony derives some material from a song which states \"I wish you could swim/ like the dolphins.\"  In addition to his David Bowie-influenced \"Heroes\" and \"Low\" symphonies, this man wrote a string quartet based on his music for a film about Yukio Mishima. This man also composed the score for a film by Godfrey Reggio which consists of time-lapse and slow-motion footage of traffic patterns and clouds among others. For 10 points, identify this contemporary composer who wrote the music for the film Koyaanisqatsi and the opera Einstein on the Beach.", "answer": "Philip Glass", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Auditory", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A study by the University of Minnesota about this project counted 25 trillion of its so-called \"persistent word views\" and found that nearly half of those PWVs was attributed to less than 0.1% of all possible sources. A 10th anniversary survey of this project showed that barely 10% of its population was female, which worried CEO Sue Gardner of the Foundation that runs it. The 2007 development of a namesake scanner for this project allowed tracing of anonymous changes made to this project to institutions like Congress and the CIA, a link that could determine violations of its Neutral Point of View policy. A notable 2005 study by Nature controversially concluded that this project was just as reliable as the Encyclopedia Britannica, despite being crowd-sourced. For 10 points, name this free, online encyclopedia.", "answer": "English Wikipedia [prompt on \"Wikimedia\"]", "category": "Trash"}, {"question": "One city on western edge of this region is known as La Villa Sur, and the city of Calama is located in the interior of this region where the Church of San Pedro is located. The Paranel Observatory is located in this region because there is little interference from artificial light or radio waves. Part of this region receives a fog known as the Camanchaca which produces enough moisture to support lichens and some cacti and the Loa River flows through this region. The Cordillera de la Sal are located in this region that is surrounded on the east by Cordillera Domeyko. This region is composed mainly of salt basins, sand and Felsic lava flows, which have led it to be compared to Mars, and parts of this region have not seen rain in over 400 years. For 10 points, name this driest desert in the world, located mostly in Chile.", "answer": "Atacama Desert  ", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "One of this author's poems declares \"Life, like a dome of many-coloured glass / Stains the white radiance of Eternity\" and claims \"Flowers, ruins, statues, music, words, are weak / The glory they transfuse with fitting truth to seek\" in a series of stanzas beginning \"Go thou to Rome.\" This author depicted a figure marked by the words, \"'I AM GOD, AND KING, AND LAW!\" in a poem imploring Englishmen not to resist soldiers massacring them, which ends \"Ye are many \u00c2\u2013 they are few.\" This author wrote a poem declaring \"Naught may endure but Mutability,\" as well an elegy which repeatedly laments \"Weep for\" the title character \u00c2\u2013 \"he is dead!\" This author of \"The Mask of Anarchy\" mourned the death of John Keats in his poem \"Adonais.\" For 10 points, name this English poet of \"To a Skylark\" and \"Ode to the West Wind.\"", "answer": "Percy Bysshe Shelley [prompt on Shelley]", "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Rainbow tables are sometimes used in preparation for this kind of operation.  Popular tools to perform this operation include LCP, Cain and Abel and John the Ripper.  This operation is made more difficult on Unix systems through shadow files.  Stretching is a technique to slow-down brute-force approaches to this operation.  One method for performing this operation requires a lot of pre-computed data and is called a dictionary attack.  This operation is easier when the salt is either known or not used, and is complicated by the fact that a one-way trapdoor function was used to store the target of this operation.  This operation is more difficult when the target is longer and made up of non-alpha numeric symbols.  For 10 points, name this process by which one attempts to find a hidden key associated with a login.", "answer": "Password Cracking [accept equivalents for cracking like password guessing or password retrieving; accept \"key\" for \"password\" until mentioned]", "subcategory": "Science Computer Science", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "A princess of Pokis named Chione once boasted about being prettier than this goddess, who struck her dumb in retaliation. This goddess once pulled the hair off the chest of a Cyclops as a child. This goddess slayed the giants Tityos and Gration and turned Arethusa into a fountain. This goddess was born on the island of Asteria. This goddess turned a woman Zeus had raped into a bear. A Queen who was the wife of Amphion boasted about being more fertile than this goddess's mother, leading to her death. King Oeneus forgot to worship this goddess, who angrily sent the Calydonian Boar to ravage his lands. In addition to killing Callisto and Niobe, this goddess turned Actaeon into a stag for viewing her naked body. For 10 points, name this sister of Apollo and Greek goddess of the hunt.", "answer": "Artemis", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "One characters in this book teaches the word \"anglophile\" to some children by explaining that they are all anglophiles, and another character forces his daughter to mechanically recite the poem \"Lochinvar\" by Walter Scott.  The American husband Larry McCaslin turns out to be less exciting than the Irish Catholic Father Mulligan in this novel, who inspires the conversion of a woman later humiliated in traffic by members of the Communist Party. Character bounds by love laws build a boat that causes their British cousin to drown and are sexually abused at a screening of The Sound of Music in this novel, which ends with an affair between Ammu and the untouchable Velutha. Beginning as Rahel returns to Kerala and reunites with her twin Estha, for ten points, name this Booker-winning novel by Arundhati Roy.", "answer": "The God of Small Things", "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "A Caddo man named John Wilson was among the most enthusiastic supporters of this movement, which was notably studied by James Mooney. Hawthorne Wodziwob introduced a prototypical version of this movement about 20 years before the real one. The leader of this movement, who had previously displayed levitation and weather control abilities, had a vision on a January 1st solar eclipse that a five-day ritual would cleanse the land, end sickness, and resurrect the dead; that leader was named Jack Wilson or Wovoka. The specially-imbued shirts worn by some followers of this movement were unable to repel bullets as initially predicted, resulting in the Wounded Knee Massacre. For 10 points, identify this late 1890s religious movement among several Native American tribes, which believed that they would regain their land if they performed the namesake rhythmic ritual", "answer": "Ghost Dance movement", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Along with RR Leleti, this scientist used a series of Dess-Martin oxidations to synthesize Salinosporamide A from threonine ester. A recent reaction developed by him involves using Indium-3 catalyzed cationic cascades to form polycycles. This man popularized the use of PCC as a gentle oxidizing agent, and he developed a series of total syntheses of prostaglandins early in his career. He also developed a method of using sulfonium ylides to from epoxides. This chemist developed a series of versatile oxazaborolidine catalysts, which can catalyze a reduction named for him, Bakshi, and Shibata.  Along with Woodward, this man pioneered the field of total synthesis, and also developed a method of visualizing a synthetic pathway by working backwards from the product. For 10 points, name this Harvard organic chemist and 1990 Nobel prizewinner who developed the method of retrosynthesis.", "answer": "Elias James Corey", "subcategory": "Science Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In one of these paintings, the subject holds a kris sword over his left shoulder and is dressed as an oriental potentate. Another of these borrows the pose from Raphael's Portrait of Baldassare Castiglione and is one of only two where the subject faces to the left. X-radiographs have revealed that the artist planned to include a white cap in the last of these, while another late one showcases the subject's anxiety over his recent bankruptcy and was part of the collection of Benjamin Altman. The artist gave himself a swashbuckling costume with plumed hat in one of these with his wife Saskia, while in another of these the subject is framed by the namesake two circles in the background. For 10 points identify these paintings by the creator of The Night Watch, which depict that Dutch artist.", "answer": "Self-portraits of Rembrandt", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Visual", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "At the end of this work's second part, one character claims that the same objections raised against the Copernican system could be raised against his arguments, to which another character replies \"Yes! We have other earths.\" The ninth chapter of this work examines an a priori argument previously put forth by Samuel Clarke, while the eleventh considers Manichean origins of the universe, but concludes that it's most likely that \"first causes... have neither goodness nor malice.\" This work's fourth chapter asks whether the same rational faculty which produces order \"in the ideas of the supreme Being,\" can not equally well explain the order of the natural world, in a refutation of the cosmological argument Formulated as a conversation witnessed by the author between Philo, Cleanthes, and Demea, for 10 points, identify this work which concludes that the existence of the creator inferred from design has very few moral consequences, written by David Hume.", "answer": "Dialogues Concerning Natural Religion", "category": "Philosophy"}, {"question": "In a lattice, the product of h-bar with the wave vector of the lattice gives the crystal variety of this property, which is sometimes assigned to phonons. In 2010 Barnett resolved a century long controversy by showing that both Abraham and Minkowski had correct formulae for this quantity for light in a medium. One form of this quantity is only conserved for central forces while Planck's constant is divided by another to get the de Broglie wavelength. Relativistically this is described as a 4-vector with the relativistic energy over c being the first term. This quantity is conserved in both elastic an inelastic collisions. Appearing in the original form of Newton's Second law, the linear version of this quantity , when crossed with the position vector, gives the Angular form of this quantity. FTP, name this quantity which is always conserved and which is typically given for linear motion as mass times velocity.", "answer": "momentum [Anti prompt on linear or angular momentum before those words are mentioned]  ", "subcategory": "Science Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "His name, along with that of Buzes, was put forward by army officers as having vowed to oppose any claimant to the throne whom they did not favor when the emperor was sick with plague. That claim forced him to consent to the marriage of his daughter and heir Joannina to Anastasius, the nephew of his empress who once ordered him to depose Pope Silverius. An adopted son of this man, Theodosius, engaged in an affair with his wife, and later became a monk. He once pretended to accept the title of Emperor of the Goths. According to The Secret History of Procopius, this man was emotionally dependent on his wife Antonia, who protected them through her friendship with Empress Theodora. For 10 points, name this Byzantine general, a rival of Narses for the favor of Emperor Justinian.", "answer": "Belisarius", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One of these figures was given a pair of divine earrings by Arnahak, and there is a dispute whether that figure was a woman. The mother of another one of these figures suddenly felt compelled to drink the moonlight on a clear night, leading to him being born glowing. Another of these figures was born after his mother had either 14 or 16 auspicious dreams. The first of these figures lives for about six hundred thousand quintillion years, while a later person to hold this position promulgated the five great vows, including truthfulness and nonviolence. For 10 points, name this position held by such figures as Lord Rishabha and Mahavira, the ford-makers and leading venerated figures of Jainism.", "answer": "Tirthankaras", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "One of this author's title characters warns his son of the undertow at the beach, which his son imagines to be a monstrous creature, the \"Under Toad\". Another of this author's title characters kills the mother with \"THE BEST BREASTS OF ALL THE MOTHERS,\" Tabitha, by hitting her with a foul ball in a little league baseball game. This author created a man who had been conceived by a dying ball turret gunner and Jenny Fields, a feminist nurse, and John Wheelwright narrates this author's novel about an eccentric dwarf. For 10 points, name this American author of The World According to Garp and A Prayer for Owen Meany.", "answer": "John Irving", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Prior to drawing cartoons for the newspaper The Vanguard, this man compiled watercolors of prostitutes into his House of Tears series. The title character of another painting is on his knees as he seems to reach beyond the top of the painting to claim fire; that work is his Prometheus. A blonde man surrounded by waves points angrily out to sea as gray people look on in one panel of another work, and shirtless men carrying machine gun rounds are smashed against rocks in this artist's The Trench. This artist painted a work at Baker Library at Dartmouth College which chronicles the migrations of native peoples, the arrival of Europeans, and the rise of industry. For 10 points, name this Mexican muralist of The Epic of American Civilization, a contemporary of Diego Rivera and David Siqueiros.", "answer": "Jose Clemente Orozco", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Visual", "category": "Fine Arts"}], "bonuses": []}